A Register of the Américo Ghioldi Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Américo Ghioldi Papers
1857-2006
2006C41
Ghioldi, Américo
64 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes (27.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The Américo Ghioldi papers in the Hoover Institution Archives document the multifaceted career of a prominent Argentine politician, journalist, and educator. Joining the Partido Socialista at an early age, Ghioldi wrote prolifically for the socialist press, principally for the newspaper he helped to edit, La Vanguardia. He was also a lecturer and orator, giving numerous talks at socialist meetings and campaign rallies. Rising to a leadership position in the Partido Socialista, he was elected repeatedly to the Argentine Cámara de Diputados de la Nación.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2006
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Chronology
1899 Born, Buenos Aires, Argentina
1917 Joins Partido Socialista
1920 Graduates from teachers' college
1924-1947 Member, editorial board, La Vanguardia
1926-1930 Member, Concejo Deliberante de la Municipalidad de Buenos Aires
1932-1943 Member, Cámara de Diputados de la Nación
1933 Juan B. Justo, sus ideas políticas, sus ideas socialistas, sus ideas filosóficos
1940s-1970s Professor, Universidad Nacional de la Plata and Universidad de Buenos Aires
1951-1955 In political exile, Montevideo, Uruguay
1955-1958 Member, Junta Consultiva Nacional
1957 Delegate, constitutional convention, Santa Fé, Argentina
1958 Founding member of Partido Socialista Democrático
1963-1966 Member, Cámara de Diputados de la Nación
1967 Ejército y política: el golpe del 28 junio de 1966
1973 Candidate for president of Argentina
1976-1979 Argentine ambassador to Portugal
1985 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
Acquired in 2006, the Américo Ghioldi papers in the Hoover Institution Archives document the multifaceted career of a prominent Argentine politician, journalist, and educator. Joining the Partido Socialista at an early age, Ghioldi wrote prolifically for the socialist press, principally for the newspaper he helped to edit, La Vanguardia. He was also a lecturer and orator, giving numerous talks at socialist meetings and campaign rallies. Rising to a leadership position in the Partido Socialista, he was elected repeatedly to the Argentine Cámara de Diputados de la Nación.
A staunch opponent of the government of Juan Perón, Ghioldi spent the early 1950s as a political exile in Uruguay. Following the military overthrow of Perón, Ghioldi returned to Argentina and joined the government as a member of the Junta Consultiva Nacional. This collaboration with military rule was controversial, as was Ghioldi's later service as Argentine ambassador to Portugal under another military junta, but throughout his political itinerary Ghioldi saw himself as remaining true to his socialist principles. After a split in the Partido Socialista in 1958, Ghioldi became one of the leaders of the Partido Socialista Democrática, in whose ranks he was active until the end of his life.
In addition to his political activities, Ghioldi taught at several Argentine universities, and showed a keen interest in the field of public education in Argentina, both as a legislator and as an author.
The largest series in the Américo Ghioldi Papers is comprised of his Speeches and Writings. These consist largely of his numerous newspaper articles, most of which deal with Argentine political issues of his era. Among the many topics addressed by Ghioldi are Peronism, economics, and the political turbulence of Argentina in the 1960s and 1970s. There are also numerous writings on the subject of education in Argentina, as well as others devoted to historical and philosophical subjects.
The Lecture Notes series in the papers contains notes used by Ghioldi in his talks on a wide variety of subjects, ranging from socialism to Argentine history.
The Correspondence series includes exchanges of letters between Ghioldi and a number of socialist personalities, including Alfredo Lorenzo Palacios and Nicolás Repetto, as well as extensive correspondence between Ghioldi and his wife, Delfina Varela Dominguez de Ghioldi.
The Biographical File contains a large number of clippings that contain accounts of Ghioldi's political activities and his many speaking engagements. Ghioldi's legislative career is documented in the Political Career File series in the papers. There are a number of lengthy recorded interviews with Ghioldi in the Sound Recordings series.
The Subject File contains significant materials relating to the Argentine educational system. The Printed Matter series contains a significant number of Argentine serial issues, ranging across the political spectrum.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 15 series: Biographical file, correspondence, speeches and writings, diaries and notebooks, lecture notes, study guides, conference materials, card files, political career file, subject file, writings by others, printed matter, photographs, sound recordings, and oversize materials
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in Stanford University's online catalog.
Subjects
Partido Socialista (Argentina); Partido Socialista Democrático (Argentina); Socialism--Argentina.; Education--Argentina.; Argentina--Politics and government--20th century.
- Biographical file, 1899-2006. (Box 1)
  Includes biographical data, clippings, personal documents, scrapbook materials, writings about Ghioldi, and other items, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Address books, undated (Folder 1: 1)
  - Bibliography of Ghioldi's publications compiled by his son, Américo, circa 2006 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Biographical data, including questionnaire, 1940-1957 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Book contract, 1962 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Caricature depicting Ghioldi, undated (Folder 1: 5)
  - Certificate of appreciation, Keren Kayemeth Leisrael, 1956 December 5 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Clippings
    - undated (Folder 1: 7)
    - 1926 (Folder 1: 8)
    - 1930-1931 (Folder 1: 9)
    - 1934-1936 (Folder 1: 10)
    - 1938-1939 (Folder 1: 11)
    - 1940-1941 (Folder 1: 12)
    - 1944 (Folder 1: 13)
    - 1945 (Folder 1: 14)
    - 1946 (Folder 1: 15)
    - 1947 (Folder 1: 16)
    - 1948 (Folder 1: 17)
    - 1949 (Folder 1: 18)
    - 1951 (Folder 1: 19)
    - 1953-1954 (Folder 1: 20)
    - 1955 (Folder 1: 21)
    - 1956 (Folder 1: 22)
    - 1957-1958 (Folder 1: 23)
    - 1959 (Folder 1: 24)
    - 1960 (Folder 1: 25)
    - 1961 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - 1962 (Folder 2: 2)
    - 1963 (Folder 2: 3)
    - 1964 (Folder 2: 4)
    - 1965 (Folder 2: 5)
    - 1966 (Folder 2: 6)
    - 1967 (Folder 2: 7)
    - 1968 (Folder 2: 8)
    - 1970 (Folder 2: 9)
    - 1971 (Folder 2: 10)
    - 1972 (Folder 2: 11)
    - 1973 (Folder 2: 12)
    - 1974 (Folder 2: 13)
    - 1975 (Folder 2: 14)
    - 1976-1979 (Folder 2: 15)
    - 1980 (Folder 2: 16)
    - 1981 (Folder 2: 17)
    - 1982 (Folder 2: 18)
    - 1983 (Folder 2: 19)
    - 1984 (Folder 2: 20)
    - 1993 (Folder 2: 21)
  - Employment and retirement records, including related correspondence
    - 1926-1960 (Folder 2: 22)
    - 1961-1963 (Folder 2: 23)
  - Leaflet announcing a political talk given by Ghioldi in Cuba, circa 1930 (Folder 2: 24)
  - Legal records, 1945-1950. (Box-folder 3: 1)
    Includes a habeas corpus petition relating to Ghioldi's detention by the Argentine government in 1945
  - Obituaries, 1984 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Personal documents
    - Birth certificate, 1899 (Folder 3: 3)
    - Identity cards, undated, 1978 (Folder 3: 4)
    - Partido Socialista and Juventud Socialista membership cards, 1917-1937 (Folder 3: 5)
    - Teaching certificate, 1917-1918 (Folder 3: 6)
  - Poems in honor of Ghioldi, 1968-1973 (Folder 3: 7)
  - Press releases, 1952-1981 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Reminiscence of Ghioldi by Antonio Guerra, undated (Folder 3: 9)
  - Scrapbook materials
    including correspondence, clippings, and photographs
    - General
      - 1954 (Folder 3: 10)
      - 1955-1956 (Folder 3: 11)
    - Arranged and annotated by Ghioldi's son, Américo
      - Volume one, 1911-1980 (Folder 3: 12-15, Box-folder 4: 1-2)
      - Volume two, 1914-1982 (Folder 4: 3-7)
      - Volume three, 1938-1979 (Folder 4: 8-11)
  - Speeches introducing Ghioldi, undated, 1965 (Folder 4: 12-13)
  - Writings about Ghioldi's political and educational careers, undated (Folder 4: 14)
- Correspondence, 1926-1983. (Box 5)
  Contains cards, letters, and enclosures, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - General
    - Birthday greetings, 1979 (Folder 5: 1-2)
    - Letters of congratulation
      - 1966 (Folder 5: 3)
      - 1967 (Folder 5: 4)
    - A, 1932-1980 (Folder 5: 5)
    - B, 1928-1979 (Folder 5: 6)
    - C, 1937-1983 (Folder 5: 7)
    - D, 1935-1974 (Folder 5: 8)
    - E, 1955-1979 (Folder 5: 9)
    - F, 1926-1963 (Folder 5: 10)
    - G, 1949-1983 (Folder 5: 11)
    - H-I, 1963-1968 (Folder 5: 12)
    - J-K, 1928-1958 (Folder 5: 13)
    - L, 1936-1967 (Folder 5: 14)
    - M, 1953-1979 (Folder 5: 15)
    - N, 1968 (Folder 5: 16)
    - O, 1967-1969 (Folder 5: 17)
    - P, 1937-1983 (Folder 5: 18)
    - Q-R, 1928-1968 (Folder 5: 19)
    - S, 1942-1979 (Folder 5: 20)
    - T, 1956-1969 (Folder 5: 21)
    - U-V, 1937-1959 (Folder 5: 22)
    - W-Z, 1957-1963 (Folder 5: 23)
  - Unidentified, 1932-1977 (Folder 5: 24)
  - Abeledo, Amaranto A., 1942-1944 (Folder 5: 25)
  - Acción Democrática Latino Americana (Zelmar Guégnolle), 1956 (Folder 5: 26)
  - Acosta, Angélica A. de, 1958-1963 (Folder 5: 27)
  - Alexander, Robert J., 1954-1962 (Folder 5: 28)
  - Alvarez, Camila G. de, 1962 (Folder 5: 29)
  - Amaya, Manuel S., 1957-1958 (Folder 5: 30)
  - Arán, Artemio, 1960-1972 (Folder 5: 31)
  - Arecena, Luis A., 1954-1955 (Folder 5: 32)
  - Barreiro, Rubén A., 1958 (Folder 5: 33)
  - Berrutti, José J., 1937-1949 (Folder 5: 34)
  - Bonatti, P. Enrique, 1955 (Folder 5: 35)
  - Borges, Jorge Luis, 1954 (Folder 5: 36)
  - Brandt, Willy, 1978 (Folder 5: 37)
  - Bronzini, Teodoro, 1968-1978 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Buira, Demetric, 1957 (Folder 6: 2)
  - Bustos Fierro, Raúl, 1961 (Folder 6: 3)
  - Campo de Griecco, Elisa, 1957-1963 (Folder 6: 4)
  - Canal Fejoo, Bernardo, 1963-1982 (Folder 6: 5)
  - Capponi, Pier Gino, 1958 (Folder 6: 6)
  - Cárcano, Rámon J., 1957 (Folder 6: 7)
  - Carreira, Emilio, 1954 (Folder 6: 8)
  - Cavallo, Osvaldo E., 1946 (Folder 6: 9)
  - Cena, Carmen, 1957 (Folder 6: 10)
  - César, Julio R., 1982 (Folder 6: 11)
  - Chertkoff, Juan, 1947 (Folder 6: 12)
  - Collados, Adolfo, 1966 (Folder 6: 13)
  - Contursi, Carlos, 1961 (Folder 6: 14)
  - Convención Evangelica Bautista (Santiago Canclini), 1957 (Folder 6: 15)
  - Correas, Edmundo, 1944 (Folder 6: 16)
  - Cosentino, Voltaire, 1982 (Folder 6: 17)
  - Croce, Benedetto, 1948-1949 (Folder 6: 18)
  - Cuesta, Manuel J. de la, 1957-1963 (Folder 6: 19)
  - Delegación de Asociaciones Israelitas Argentinas (Daniel Levy, Nehemias Resnizky), 1979 (Folder 6: 20)
  - Díaz, Pedro, 1958 (Folder 6: 21)
  - Díaz Arana, Juan José, 1948 (Folder 6: 22)
  - Dickmann, Enrique, 1946-1950 (Folder 6: 23)
  - Dubra, Arturo J., 1957 (Folder 6: 24)
  - Durán Cano, Ricardo, 1958 (Folder 6: 25)
  - Durante, Alfredo, 1963 (Folder 6: 26)
  - Espindola, Sofia, 1938-1957 (Folder 6: 27)
  - Federación Agraria Argentina (Nazareno Magnarelli, Julio B. Oroño), 1957 (Folder 6: 28)
  - Fernández, Guillermo, 1964 (Folder 6: 29)
  - Ferreira, J. Alfredo, 1933 (Folder 6: 30)
  - Fiorito, Alberto A., 1946 (Folder 6: 31)
  - Gainza Paz, 1953-1954 (Folder 6: 32)
  - Galaretto, Rodolfo N., 1956 (Folder 6: 33)
  - Ghioldi, Américo "Quito", 1949-1980 (Folder 6: 34)
  - Ghioldi, Delfina Varela Dominguez de
    - 1941 (Folder 6: 35)
    - 1952 (Folder 6: 36)
    - 1953 (Folder 6: 37)
    - 1954 (Folder 6: 38-39)
    - 1955 (Folder 6: 40)
  - Ghioldi, Manuel, 1940-1941 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - Giulitta, O. A., 1946 (Folder 7: 2)
  - Grant, Frances R., 1952-1955 (Folder 7: 3)
  - Greco, Luis del, 1958-1969 (Folder 7: 4)
  - Gutiérrez, Fermín Estrella, 1925 (Folder 7: 5)
  - Haya de la Torre, Victor, 1954 (Folder 7: 6)
  - Herrera, A., 1937 (Folder 7: 7)
  - Kirschen, Armand, 1971-1973 (Folder 7: 8)
  - Korn, Guillermo, 1953 (Folder 7: 9)
  - Labat, Juan M., undated (Folder 7: 10)
  - Latour, E. Fernández, 1962 (Folder 7: 11)
  - Linares Quintana, Segundo V., 1948-1983 (Folder 7: 12)
  - Litwin, Mateo, 1979 (Folder 7: 13)
  - Lovestone, Jay, 1954 (Folder 7: 14)
  - Lustig, Emil, 1956 (Folder 7: 15)
  - Maier, Gabriella, 1960 (Folder 7: 16)
  - Maradona, Waldino B., 1926-1957 (Folder 7: 17)
  - Martella, Julio Cesar, 1954 (Folder 7: 18)
  - Martini, Rómulo E., 1947 (Folder 7: 19)
  - Migliorini, Máximo, 1956-1977 (Folder 7: 20)
  - Molinas, Luciano F., 1961-1969 (Folder 7: 21)
  - Mondolfo, Rodolfo, 1962-1969 (Folder 7: 22)
  - Montenegro, Adelmo, 1963-1979 (Folder 7: 23)
  - Montonero, José, 1957-1979 (Folder 7: 24)
  - Mor Roig, Arturo, 1965 (Folder 7: 25)
  - Mora Rodriguez, Vicente, 1946 (Folder 7: 26)
  - Moreau de Justo, Alicia, 1954-1956 (Folder 7: 27)
  - Muñiz, Ramón A., 1950-1957 (Folder 7: 28)
  - Mutualidad del Magisterio (Manuel Cuestas Acosta), 1980-1981 (Folder 7: 29)
  - Nuñez, Juan José, 1969 (Folder 7: 30)
  - Ordoñez, Marcos, 1976 (Folder 7: 31)
  - Orgaz, Alfredo, 1963-1970 (Folder 7: 32)
  - Orgaz, Jorge Arturo, 1958-1979 (Folder 7: 33)
  - Otero, Dino, 1958 (Folder 7: 34)
  - Palacios, Alfredo Lorenzo, 1933-1957 (Folder 7: 35)
  - Palacios Molina, Eduardo, 1960-1961 (Folder 7: 36)
  - Partido Socialista (Rodolfo di Núbila), 1942 (Folder 7: 37)
  - Partido Socialista Democrática (Aldo Luis Arrighi, Ismael Alberto Torres), 1983 (Folder 7: 38)
  - Perez Catán, Mauricio, 1958 (Folder 7: 39)
  - Pizzurno, Pablo A., 1934-1947 (Folder 7: 40)
  - Pompilio, Marcos, 1951 (Folder 7: 41)
  - Prieto, Indalecio, 1953-1954 (Folder 7: 42)
  - Ramírez, Saturnino, 1972 (Folder 7: 43)
  - Rawson, Arturo, 1944 (Folder 7: 44)
  - Rawson, Franklin Dellepiane, 1946 (Folder 7: 45)
  - Repetto, Nicolás, 1940-1964 (Folder 7: 46)
  - Rey Alvarez, G. A., 1955 (Folder 7: 47)
  - Rivas, Ricardo, 1940 (Folder 7: 48)
  - Rodriguez Araya, Estudio, 1947 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Romano, Manuel, 1950 (Folder 8: 2)
  - Romano, Nicolás, 1946 (Folder 8: 3)
  - Romualdi, Serafino, 1956 (Folder 8: 4)
  - Sagarna, Antonio, 1940-1949 (Folder 8: 5)
  - Sala Mendez, Ernesto, 1954 (Folder 8: 6)
  - Santilli, Carlos, 1950 (Folder 8: 7)
  - Santos Gollan, José, 1949 (Folder 8: 8)
  - Schultz de Mantovani, Fryda, 1963 (Folder 8: 9)
  - Segriá, Ramón, 1968-1980 (Folder 8: 10)
  - Soares, Mario, 1978 (Folder 8: 11)
  - Solari, Juan Antonio, 1948-1961 (Folder 8: 12)
  - Thomas, Norman, 1954 (Folder 8: 13)
  - Tournier, Adolfo León, 1958 (Folder 8: 14)
  - Universidad de Buenos Aires, 1956-1960 (Folder 8: 15)
  - Universidad Nacional de la Plata, 1940-1964 (Folder 8: 16)
  - Velluz, Luisa B. de, 1935 (Folder 8: 17)
  - Verde Tello, Pedro A., 1963-1970 (Folder 8: 18)
  - Vilardo, Eugenio B., 1978 (Folder 8: 19)
  - Villareal, José R., 1977 (Folder 8: 20)
- Speeches and Writings, 1919-1982.
  Contains articles, monographs, and speeches, arranged chronologically
  - "Acontecimientos importantes en el campo de la educación a partir de Revolución de Mayo.", Undated (Folder 8: 21)
    Typescript
  - "Al país.", Undated (Folder 8: 22)
  - "Algunas acontaciones sobre aspectos diversos de nuestra lucha política y social.", Undated (Folder 8: 23)
  - "Algunos aspectos de política escolar.", Undated (Folder 8: 24)
  - "Algunos puntos sobre instrucción primaria.", Undated (Folder 8: 25)
  - "Antecedentes legislativos defacto y culturales del proyecto oficialista de reforma constitucional.", Undated (Folder 8: 26)
    Holograph and typescript
  - "La asamblea del año 13," speech., Undated (Folder 8: 27)
  - "Autonomia municipal.", Undated (Folder 8: 28)
  - "Autoridad del pueblo y el derecho del padre.", Undated (Folder 8: 29)
  - campaign speech., Undated (Folder 8: 30)
  - "Civilización y barbarie.", Undated (Folder 8: 31)
  - "Cuerpo extraño en el gobierno," La Vanguardia., Undated (Folder 8: 32)
  - "Datos, ideas y proposiciones sobre la cuestión agraria.", Undated (Folder 8: 33)
  - "El derecho de la familia y de la educación.", Undated (Folder 8: 34)
  - "La educación en la constitución de la nación y de las provincias.", Undated (Folder 8: 35)
  - "En el dia del maestro.", Undated (Folder 8: 36)
    Holograph
  - "La escuela, el trabajo y el trabajador.", Undated (Folder 8: 37)
    Printed copy
  - "Estudiantes de la libertad.", Undated (Folder 8: 38)
  - "Exigencias actuales del nacionalismo.", Undated (Folder 8: 39)
  - "Filosofía de la escuela para adultos.", Undated (Folder 8: 40)
  - "La generación argentina del 80 y el liberalismo escolar," speech., Undated (Folder 8: 41)
  - "La historia y la anti-historia. Montoneros, liberalismo y socialsimo.", Undated (Folder 8: 42)
  - "Horacio Rivarola, educador.", Undated (Folder 8: 43)
  - "Las ideas de J. Alfredo Ferreiro.", Undated (Folder 8: 44)
  - "Imagen del hombre.", Undated (Folder 8: 45)
  - "Importancia de la ayuda visual en la enseñanza.", Undated (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - "¿Independencia económica ahora?"., Undated (Folder 9: 2)
  - "Institucionalizar un régimen o institucionalizar una nación.", Undated (Folder 9: 3)
  - "Legislación escolar nacional.", Undated (Folder 9: 4)
  - "Liberalismo y positivismo.", Undated (Folder 9: 5)
  - May Day speech., Undated (Folder 9: 6)
  - "No es culto del pasado sino ejercicio de la historia.", Undated (Folder 9: 7)
  - notes on education in Argentina., Undated (Folder 9: 8)
  - notes on fascism., Undated (Folder 9: 9)
  - notes on Jean Jaurès., Undated (Folder 9: 10)
  - notes on liberalism., Undated (Folder 9: 11)
  - notes on political philosophy., Undated (Folder 9: 12)
  - notes on religious education., Undated (Folder 9: 13)
  - notes on Shakespeare., Undated (Folder 9: 14)
  - "Organización de la enseñanza primaria y media.", Undated (Folder 9: 15)
  - "Para el resurgimiento.", Undated (Folder 9: 16)
  - "Pascal Guagianone en la política educacional argentina", Undated
    - Notes (Folder 9: 17)
    - Typescript (Folder 9: 18)
  - "El pensamiento económico.", Undated (Folder 9: 19)
  - "Política educativa como parte del plan histórico.", Undated (Folder 9: 20)
  - "Por un primero de Mayo socialmente renaciente.", Undated (Folder 9: 21)
  - "El pueblo y el ejercito.", Undated (Folder 9: 22)
  - "¿Quién manda? ¿Cómo lo consiguió?"., Undated (Folder 9: 23)
  - "Razones históricos para el socialismo.", Undated (Folder 9: 24)
  - remarks prepared for General Pedro Aramburu., Undated (Folder 9: 25)
  - review of book by Manuel Ramirez., Undated (Folder 9: 26)
  - "Sarmiento creador del magisterio argentino," summary of speech., Undated (Folder 9: 27)
  - "¿Sarmiento un deformador de Argentina?"., Undated (Folder 9: 28)
  - speech on constitutional reform., Undated (Folder 9: 29)
  - speech on economic situation in Argentina, Radio El Mundo., Undated (Folder 9: 30)
  - speech on education., Undated (Folder 9: 31)
  - speech on political situation in Argentina., Undated (Folder 9: 32)
  - speech on political situation in Latin America, Montevideo, Uruguay., Undated (Folder 9: 33)
  - speech on residency law., Undated (Folder 9: 34)
  - speech on socialism., Undated (Folder 9: 35)
  - speech on socialist ideology., Undated (Folder 9: 36)
  - speech on the meaning of May Day., Undated (Folder 9: 37)
  - speech to Socialist Party assembly., Undated (Folder 9: 38)
  - speech to teachers., Undated (Folder 9: 39)
  - "El tema de la violencia.", Undated (Folder 9: 40)
  - "Teoría y práctica de la democracia en la Argentina," summary of speech., Undated (Folder 9: 41)
  - "Testimonio.", Undated (Folder 9: 42)
  - "Los topicos fundamentales del preambulo.", Undated (Folder 9: 43)
  - "Los trabajadores y la década de experiencia de un gran error.", Undated (Folder 9: 44)
  - writing on Benedetto Croce., Undated (Folder 9: 45)
  - writing on constitutional reform., Undated (Folder 9: 46)
  - writing on Domingo Faustino Sarmiento, Undated (Box 10)
    - Holograph (Folder 10: 1)
    - Typescript drafts (Folder 10: 2)
  - writing on education in Argentina, Undated
    - Holograph (Folder 10: 3)
    - Typescript (Folder 10: 4)
  - writing on education and Sarmiento., Undated (Folder 10: 5)
  - writing on history and socialism., Undated (Folder 10: 6)
  - writing on socialism and economics., Undated (Folder 10: 7)
  - "Asistencia libre en el profesorado.", 1919 (Folder 10: 8)
  - "Gobierno de las escuelas normales.", 1919 (Folder 10: 9)
  - "Reglamento interno de escuelas normales.", 1919 (Folder 10: 10)
  - "El valor de la ciencia.", 1919 (Folder 10: 11)
  - "Los exámenes," Atlántida., 1919 March (Folder 10: 12)
    Holograph and printed copy
  - speech on education., 1920 (Folder 10: 13)
  - speech to teachers' congress., 1920 November 6 (Folder 10: 14)
  - "Sobre el proximo voto general.", 1921 December 5 (Folder 10: 15)
  - Nacionalismo en la enseñanza., 1924 (Folder 10: 16)
  - "Disciplina y libertad partidarias," La Vanguardia., 1927 June 19 (Folder 10: 17)
  - "La extension del saber," La Vanguardia., 1929 July 28-29 (Folder 10: 18)
  - "Los movimientos políticos traducen tendencias generales del pensaminento," La Vanguardia., 1930 January 1 (Folder 10: 19)
  - "Ni regenerador," La Vanguardia., 1930 January 15 (Folder 10: 20)
  - "Estado providencial," La Vanguardia., 1930 April 15 (Folder 10: 21)
  - "La juventud y el socialismo," La Vanguardia., 1930 May 11 (Folder 10: 22)
  - "El Partido Socialista, escuela de orientación intelectual," La Vanguardia., 1931 April 4 (Folder 10: 23)
  - "La juventud universitaria y la política.", 1931 July (Folder 10: 24)
  - "Acción y pensamiento renovador," La Vanguardia., 1931 August 16 (Folder 10: 25)
  - "Mitin en el salón Augusteo," La Vanguardia., 1931 September 18 (Folder 10: 26)
  - "Pedagogia," Revista Socialista., 1932 February (Folder 10: 27)
  - "No está en peligro nacionalidad," La Vanguardia., 1932 August 17 (Folder 10: 28)
  - "¿Federal o Unitario?"., 1933 (Folder 10: 29)
  - "Nuestra obra duradera," La Vanguardia., 1933 January 2 (Folder 10: 30)
  - "El patrón oro, los precios y los salaries," La Vanguardia., 1933 January 12 (Folder 10: 31)
  - "La política monetaria," La Vanguardia., 1933 January 13 (Folder 10: 32)
  - "Incompatibilidades reales e incompatibilides ficticias," La Vanguardia., 1933 April 13 (Folder 10: 33)
  - "Consecuencias de las finanzas oligárquicas," La Vanguardia., 1933 April 15 (Folder 10: 34)
  - "Los intereses nacionales y el socialismo," La Vanguardia., 1933 May 1 (Folder 10: 35)
  - "Lucha incesante y renovada," El Trabajo., 1933 May 1 (Folder 10: 36)
  - "Política de las lineas paralelas," El Socialista., 1933 May 1 (Folder 10: 37)
  - "Afirmación de confianza," La Vanguardia., 1933 June 12 (Folder 10: 38)
  - "Síntesis del discurso del diputado Ghioldi," La Vanguardia., 1933 December 8 (Folder 10: 39)